<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_jaraid.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt xml:lang="en">
            <title>Kawkab Amīrkā</title>
            <title type="sub">Digital Edition</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI version</resp>
               <persName>Till Grallert</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date when="2015-05-01">1 May 2015</date>
            </edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Created the original TEI P5 XML file</resp>
               <persName xml:id="pTG">Till Grallert</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>The digital text is freely available for re-use.</p>
            <p>The image files are subject to the following copyright and provided by the Center for Research Libraries:</p>
            <p>Materials digitized by the Center for Research Libraries are intended for the personal educational and research use of students, scholars, and other researchers of the CRL member community. Copyrighted images and texts are not to be reproduced, displayed, distributed, broadcast, or downloaded for other purposes without the expressed, written permission of the copyright owner.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Some prose providing information on the source of the text</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The TEI file was produced for teaching a course on the basics of scholarly encoding
               using TEI P5 and XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>providing information on our decisions concerning the actual transcription of a
               newspaper structure into a TEI P5 XML file</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2015-05-31">Generated this file by stripping all mark-up from file:/BachCloud/BTSync/FormerDropbox/2015%20TEI%20Introduction/xml/example-Kawkab-v1.TEIP5.xml</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>
      
         
      
      
         
            
               
               
                  
                  
                     العدد ١
                  
                  
                     
                     Ottoman crescent and star
                  
                  
                  السنة الاولى
               
               
               
                  
                  
                     
                        قيمة الاشتراك
                        في نيو يورك ريالات اميركية يضاف اليها
                           اجرةالبريد لسائر مدن الولايات تلمتحدة وفي الممالك الخارجية
                           ثمانية عشر فرنكًا خالصة اجرة البريد 
                        ---
                     
                     
                        جميع الرسائل التي ترد الينا ينبغي ان تكون خالصةاجرة البريد باسم
                              الدكتور ابراهيم ونجيبيوسف
                              عربيلي منشئي الجريدةولا ترد لاصحابها نشرت ام لم
                           تنشر
                        ---
                     
                     
                        اجرة الاعلانات
                        في الصفحة الاخيرة عن كل سطر ١٥ سنتاً وللمشتركين ١٠وفي غير الصفحة
                           الاخيرة ٢٠ سنتاً وللمشتركين ١٥واما الرسائل الخصوصية فحكمها حكم
                           الاعلانات
                        ---
                     
                     
                        ومتعلقات المطبعة الشرقية مع مديرها ارتين افندي بتركيانالدفع
                           سلفًا
                     
                  
                  
                  
                     كوكب اميركا
                     ---
                     جريدة سياسية علمية تجارية
                        ادبية
                     ---
                     تصدر كل يوم الجمعة من كل اسبوع
                  
                  
                  
                     Subscription Rates.
                     ---
                     For New York, per annum, - $ 3.00,To which will be added tho postage to
                        allcities in the United States.In all Foreign Countries, - 18
                        Frcs.including Postage.All communications relating to busines
                        withThe Oriental Publishing House, must be ad-dressed to its
                        Manager,ARTEEN EFFENDI PETRAKIAN,and those relating to "Kawkab
                        America," toDr. A. &amp; N.J. Arbeely,Editors and
                        Proprietors45 Pearl Street,New York, U.S.A.
                  
               
               
               
                  نيو يورك
                     الجمعة في  ١٥ نيسان غ و٣ ش سنة ١٨٩٢
                     موافق ١٩ رمضان ١٣٠٩
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                  Reproduction of the Ottoman coat of arms / Sultanic seal
               
               
                  كومب اميركا
                  يشرف هذا الكوكب في جانب الغرب الاقصى تذكاراًجميلاً به هلال الدولة والامة
                     والوطن فيرسم شعارهاوفخارها من وراءِ الاتلانتيك رسماً جليلاً له في
                     قلوبالشرقيين في هذه الديار ...
                  
               
               
                  فليعش سلطاننا عبد الحميد
                  بل لا عجب اذا عد هذا الكوكب من احدى السيارات التيتدور حول ذلك القطب الثابت
                     على ضفاف البوسفورالذي سدور حوله البران والبحران ترتد عنها اعين
                     الحاسدين...
                  
                  
               
               
               
                  اعتذار
                  كان في النية اصدار جريدتنا هذه في اليوم السادسعشر من شهر شعبان تيمناً بيوم
                     جلالة سلطاننا الاعظموقد اعلنا ذلك في بعض جرائد سوريا بلسان وكيلنا
                     العاموانيس افندي بتراكيان مدير تلغراف مركز متصرفية جبللبنان لكن تأخر
                     ورود مواد الطباعة في العربية عنالوجود الكورنتينات سبب تاجيل اصدارها الى
                     هذا اليوموهي على كل حال لا تفتر عن ذكر مولاها العادل فيكل آ ن
                  ---
               
               
                  لمحة طارق
                  مرَّ على اوريا دور لم نسمع به سوى تجهيز العساكرونجميع الذخائر حتى اصبحت
                     ممالكها تنتفض خشية نسيمحادث ...
                  
               
               
                  عودة لامح
                  نازل القحط ارض الروس فاشتف ماء الاجسادوحل فيهم ثقيلا وبيلا في يقعة من
                     دبارهم فيها اثنان
                  
                  ---
               
               
                  اخبار محلية
                  
                  
               
               
                  مباداة خيرٍ بشر
                  
                  
                  ---
               
               
               
                  
                  
                  
               
               
               
            
         
         
            
               
               
                  Kawkab America
                     
               
               
               
               
                  Vo. 1. No. 1 New York, Friday, April 15, 1892.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Kawkab erica
                  Vo.1. No.1. New York, Friday, 
               
               
               
                  "Kawkab America"
                  Office. 45 Pearl Street
                  An Oriental Weekly devoted to the development of direct helpful relations and good understanding between the East and the West
               
               
                  Introduction.
                  In entering the field of journalism, so ably occuped by a host of the most
                     accomplished and progressive writers of the age, we feel called upon for a word
                     of explanation. We desire that our position may be clearly understood.
                  From time immemorial a wide gulf has separated the nations of the East from
                     those of the West, and this has been the result of diametrically opposite
                     conceptions of character, of customs and civilization entertained by each
                     toward the other, all arising from ignorance of the nature and condition of the
                     respective peoples.
                  It is an undoubted fact that the western man does not undertsand the oriental
                     as the latter really is, and persists in placing him in an imaginary sphere
                     utterly at variance with the reality.
                  On the other hand, to the western mind the people of the west, with their
                     matchless activity and awe inspiring progress in the field of practical science
                     and discovery, are still objects of suspicion. They are looked upon as people
                     with whom might makes right, ready to utilize every chance for
                     self-aggrandisement, regardless of the methods or means they employ. The
                     conquest and interference of the European powers in the various sections of
                     Asia and Africa strengthen this belief. There has been no step taken toward a
                     better understanding. The west has seemed to forget that notwithstanding the
                     lack of progress in eastern civilization caused by long-continued wars and
                     other disadvatages, there are quite as many virtues and noble traits of
                     character among the sons of Shem as among those of Japhet.
                  ...
               
               
                  H.I.His Imperial Majesty Abdul-Hamid Khan.
                  Among all the Sultans who have sat upon the throne of the Ottoman Empire, none
                     has achieved greater success in raising the Ottoman people to a higher position
                     among the nations of the Earth, than the present "Great Price of the Faithful"
                     Abdul-Hamid.
                  At the time of his coming into power, the financial condition and internal
                     affairs of the Empire, presented one of the most difficult and perplexing
                     problems that have ever confronted a ruler assuming the great responsibilities
                     of government. The severe reaction from the war with Russia and the trying
                     condition of affairs at that time, combined with the reckless machinations and
                     intrigues of European diplomats, required unusual ability and wisdom for their
                     management and counteracting their effects. They seemed to have appealed at the
                     outset to the unbounded patriotism and matchless energy of this wonderful
                     Padishah who determined to protect the interests of his people at all hazards
                     and make them feel the beneficent results of a pure, vigorous, and progressive
                     Ottoman Policy.
                  ...
               
               
                  The outrages on the Syrian Colony.
                  For some time past a certain class of ruffians infested the neighborhood of
                     lower Washington and Greenwich Sts, have annouyed many of our countrymen, and
                     people of other nationalities with molestations and persecutions, that could
                     barely be expected from Barbarians in the Wilds of Africa.
                  It seems as if it has become a sport for some of these thugs and rascals to vie
                     with each other in their abuse of inoffensive and peaceful people who have
                     patiently and in the interest of peace, stood gross insults and aggressive
                     maltreatments, which should have been made impossible not only by the proper
                     authorities, but also by the aggrieved parties themselves, who ought never to
                     forget that "Self-protection in America, as well as in Syria, is among the
                     first laws of Nature."
                  These outrages and acts of lawlessness have been brought time and again to the
                     attention of those whose duty it is to see that they are stopped, and their
                     perpetrators brought to speedy punishment, so that a wholeseome and profitable
                     lesson may be taught to soem of those who are most notorious in their
                     commission. The matter was also brought before the Supt. of Police in the form
                     of a memorial from the "Syrian Union of America," and was laid before Public
                     through various articles in the Press, which was unanimous in its unqualified
                     condemnation and urgent recommendation for the adoption of vigorous measures to
                     prevent similar shameful occurances. All these things seemed to have availed
                     nothing
                  More disgraceful assaults were committed again recently on several of our
                     countrymen under the eyes of the police, and resulted in the crippling of
                     several, and almost the murder of a young and respectable woman.
                  ...
               
               
                  Persia of To-day.
                  [By S. Al-Saiyid]
                  
                  
               
               
                  Oriental Miscealany.
                  
                  
               
            
         
      
      
            
         
   </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
