<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>PRO FO 618/3, Despatches to Constantinople, quarterly report, Hedjaz railway,
                    reports on local politics etc., 1908</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding in TEI</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="pers_TG">Till Grallert</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>The digital text is freely available for re-use.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
            <p>Some prose providing information on the source of the text</p>
         </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>Some of the letters in this file have been transcribed as detailed as possible to demonstrate the application of TEI P5 to an introductory course</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Hyphenation that might occur at the end of a line has been silently removed</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>In case spelling or punctuation have been corrected in the transcription, it has been done without further comment.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <TEI xml:id="ProFo_618-3_Damascus-30_19080803" xml:lang="en">
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>PRO FO 618/3 Damascus Draft 30, Devey to Lowther 3 Aug. 1908</title>
                    <author>George Pollard Devey</author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <p/>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
               <p>Some prose providing information on the source of the text</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        
        <text>
         <body>
            <p>
            
                
                
                    Ex-Mushir Fuad P. released
                    August 3, 1908
                    Dft
                        Sir Gerald A. Lowther K.C.M.G.,C.B., 
                        
                                Cple
                                Constantinople
                            
                         No. 30
                        29 30
                    42 Emb.
                    Sir, I have the honour to report to Y.E. that the General Amnesty
                        granted by 
                                H.I.M.
                                His Imperial Majesty
                             the Sultan to all Political
                            criminals was after some hesitation taken to
                        exciles was after some hesitation taken to include the Ex-Mushir
                            Fuad Pasha who has been imprisoned under the
                        strictest confinement for the last six and a half years; and on the
                            evening of
                        about  on the 30th. ultimo the
                            Commander of the 5th A.C.Colonel of Gendarmerie
                        went in person, dismissed the numerous guards around the prisoner’s house of
                        confinement and communicated to him the news of his being at liberty to go
                        wherever he likes. On the following day
                        Fuad P
                                .
                                asha
                            
                        w while going for the prayer in the Great
                            Mosque, was very enthusiastically applauded &amp; cheered by
                            
                        the thousands
                        crowds of people who assembled &amp; walked before &amp;
                            after his
                        mobbing his carriage &amp; showing their extreme
                            joy for
                        happiness at his release, in every possible way.
                            Even inside the Mosque after the usual Friday prayers he
                            was surrounded &amp; his hand shaken or kissed by great numbers with
                            much emotion. It is credible that had he not been set at liberty for the
                                31st being Friday some noisy demonstration
                            manifestation w
                                .
                                oul
                            d have been called to protest against his detention.
                    On the evening of the 31st ultimo he attended the demonstration
                        held in the Defterdar Garden in honour of the
                        Constitution and his presence there added very greatly
                            toaccentuated the zeal and joy manifested
                            byof the public crowded in the garden
                        crowd. Most of the notables and chief officials have already
                        called at on Fuad Pasha in his house &amp;
                        expressed sympathy. He will probably leave Damascus
                        for Cple.
                        by the end of this week the 6th or 7th
                            inst.
                        &amp; meet his&amp; reunite his numerous family
                            of 12 sons &amp; 8 daughters:for the last a 3
                            years his son aged 13aged 11 years old son has been boarding
                            for the last 3 years in the local Idadie high school &amp;
                            permitted to visit his father a month, but  on each occasion
                            with a company here.During his stay here he had the society
                            of one wife, two daughters and one son now 14 yrs. old.
                    Some of the foreign Consuls had called in the Friday afternoon, &amp; I
                        arranged to visit him on the morning of the 1st inst. when I
                        had the privilege of an affecting interview, as
                        he was still deeply moved by long suffering. Many visitors were present
                        &amp; constantly coming &amp; going, as also the Acting
                            Russian Consul &amp; Russian Dragoman &amp;
                            FerikLiva
                        Husini Pasha of of
                        the Technical
                        fortification worksDepartment &amp; various officers
                        &amp; Ulema, many being known to H. Exy. of you. In the afternoon he
                        returned my visit at the Consulate &amp; I understand is punctiliously
                        returning as many visits of great &amp; small as possible. When I took
                        leave, he courteously accompanied on a little way &amp; made profession to
                        my private care of continued Anglophile sentiments.
                    On Sat. afternoon I felt that I 
                            cd.
                            could
                         not but let Him. Exy. know that Hr. M.y has
                        offered congratulations in the matter of the inestimable boon of the
                        reestablished Constitution, &amp; trusted that recent  wd.
                            lead with athe new departure may tend to better Gov.t
                        &amp; true reforms in Turkey. I have etc.
                                G.P.D.The Marshal’s very
                            outspoken opinions show that he abides by the well known liberal
                            opinions professed throughout his career.
                    I have etc. 
                                G.P.D.
                                George Pollard Devey
                            
                
            
        </p>
         </body>
      </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI xml:id="ProFo_618-3_Damascus-33_19080912" xml:lang="en">
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>PRO FO 618/3 Damascus Draft 33, Devey to Lowther 12 Aug. 1908</title>
                    <author>George Pollard Devey</author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <p/>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
               <p>Some prose providing information on the source of the text</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        
        <text>
         <body>
            <p>
            
                
                
                    State of affairs in Damascus relating to the new Regime
                    Damascus.August 12. 1908.
                    DftSir G.A. LowtherCpleNo. 33
                    Sir,with ref.ce to my des.ch No. 29 of the 3.rd ins. I have the honour
                        to report some of theupon the more interesting
                        proceedings that took place here since that date
                            respectingconnected with the new Constitutional
                        movement.
                    The ManyLoud Popular demonstrations and
                            happygreat manifestations of joy with
                        illuminations and street decorations have been going on in all the
                            quarters of the city showing the utmost zeal and enthusiasm on the part
                            of the public who hardly understand the situation or appreciate the
                            foundation of their joy; but fortunately no
                        throughout the city from were continuous from the 31st ult.imo
                            until yesterday, some of them attended also by numerous
                                masses
                            throngs from neighbouring villages; though indeed few
                                present could have really appreciated at their true value
                            the great privileges accorded. Happily scarcely a
                        slight accidents occurred, though
                            withfearing the excessive use of rifles +
                        revolvers bullets was continuous
                        was at first rather dangerous; except that a bullet broke the
                        tramway electric wire which fell on the mob &amp; the current killed three
                        people &amp; injoured
                        three
                        two others.
                    Five general meetings were held in honour of the Constitution four of which
                        in two public gardens attended by several thousands of spectators including
                        the Vali and the three Mushirs now in Damascus, and one in a large theatre;
                        these meetings were given by provisional societies, military and civil, and
                        on each occasion more than a dozen speeches were delivered by various
                        speakers of liberal views, which were almost without exception temperate and
                        conducive to allay excitement.
                    Army officers started a club under the name of ‘Liberty’
                        and inaugurated it on the 10th instant; one of the conditions
                        for joining the club being supporting the Constitution; and the membership
                        may be granted to worthy civilians also. The members amount now to more than
                        a hundred officers who joined in the last two days.
                    The liberal civilians are now forming another club with nearly similar
                        conditions as those of the  of the “Liberty Club”
                        and undoubtedly most of the chief notables will join it.
                    No serious steps have been taken as yet on any side towards the elections for
                        the Parliament but the clubs above mentioned intend to give their influence
                        for the choice of competent persons who are not yet indicated.
                    The Union &amp; Progress Society, whose individual members
                        can only be conjectend [?] vaguely here, is practically directed[?], the
                        Government gestation, military and administration in a prudent and energetic
                        way. The Vali at the Society’s demand began on the 10th instant
                        to dismiss or compel resignation of corrupt and mischievous officials such
                        as the the Chief of Police Oman Jamal, Said
                            Effendi Banna, the Muhassebji, the Caim.ms of
                            Douma, Zibadan &amp;
                            Dera’a Cazas, the last being a cousin of
                            Izzet Pasha. The Alai Bey of Gendarmerie is also
                        likely to be dismissed with a particularly corrupt Major Ahmed
                            Bey of the Zaptiehs and several other functionaries of ill
                        repute will be in similar case [?], for the  the society intend to
                        improve the government departments gradually so as to replace the old
                        corrupt system by a new hones set of officials who are not to be found at
                        once.
                    There is some discontent on the part of the ulema and certain leaders in town
                        for the Union &amp; Progress Society, is going forward in
                        its own way and removing officials without consulting them, but there seem
                        no reason to fear that such discontent might provoke any substantial
                        resistance, at present.
                    Izzet Pasha’s partisans and creatures here are not few,
                        but, having the public sentiments against them, they are rather afraid for
                        their own safety and trying to gain as many liberal friends as possible.
                    It is a good things that the demonstrations &amp; calling together
                        of crowds are now at an end for it is evident that the loss of the 
                        prestige o the government and the palpable decrease of its influence might
                        easily afford an opportunity for malcontents to provoke disturbance and
                        cause trouble in order to show the bad results of the liberal views.
                    It is true that there are no symptoms of animosity here between Moslems and
                        Christians but, as is always the case when the government power relaxes and
                        the public order endangered the weaker element would be the actual sufferer.
                        For this reason the Christians and Jews here rather felt a certain amount of
                        anxiety during the last fortnight, but the liberal chiefs among Moslems have
                        been all the time preaching equality and emphasising the necessity of order
                        and good behaviour.
                    As to the effect of promulgating the constitution in the other towns of this
                        Vilayet, very little can be said, for the people of the 
                        Hauran and Kerak Sanjak are
                        too ignorant to appreciate the difference between autocratic and
                        constitutional government” […]
                     In conclusion, I might add here that a pessimistic observer does not
                            fail to see some faint reasons for anxiety in Damascus and would, but
                            not without hesitation, foretell the rise of antagonistic parties who
                            might deal with each other corporally and endanger the public security.
                            The garrison of the town, I am sorry to say, is rather too small to cope
                            with such emergencies if they would ever come to action 
                        Trouble so easily arises out of small incidents, e.g. the Bab Tuma
                            tumult (v. No. 30 of Aug 2/07[?]) or again the death of a policeman in
                            1902 that one cannot but feel some slight uneasiness without being
                            unduly pessimistic. Then again the conditions of the city are very
                            dissimilar from those of most others, in having here great notables of
                            various classes, races, &amp; ideas, accustomed to influence and power;
                            and there is a 
                         new element in the presence of the Hamidiyye
                            troops still in temporary camp here the wide +rambling extent
                        of the town with the relative fewness of troops in garrison, so many being
                        employed in the Hejaz railway construction, do not concur
                        to allay such apprehension, at a moment when local police are likely to be
                        called to a reckoning as in general more or less corrupt + inefficient.
                
            
        </p>
         </body>
      </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI xml:id="ProFo_618-3_Damascus_19081001_1" xml:lang="en">
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>PRO FO 618/3 Damascus 51 draft, General Report for September Quarter,
                        Devey to Lowther 1 Oct. 1908</title>
                    <author>George Pollard Devey</author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <p/>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
               <p>Some prose providing information on the source of the text</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        
        <text>
         <body>
            <p>
            
                
                    
                    General Report for September Quarter
                    DamascusOctober 1. 1908.
                    DftSir G.A. LowtherCpleNo. 51
                    Sir,I have the honour to submit herwith mya
                        general report for
                        on events during the last quarter.
                     The great ‘coup d’Etat’ which took place in Turkey on
                        the 24th July occupied all minds and engaged
                        aroused every emotion with the proclamation of the Constitution,
                        in Damascus as in all other important centres in the
                            Empire. The chief  interests
                        Among its results worthy of remark here during this
                            time were 
                            (a) celebrations and festivities
                            (b) dismissal or withdrawalresignation of
                                notoriously corrupt officials
                            (c) formation of clubs and associations
                            (d) parliamentary elections
                            (e) reforms in various governmental departments.
                            (f) release or rehabilitation
                                made to of political exiles or persons
                        
                    Rejoicings and joyful manifestation came now
                        are only coming now to an end, after lasting more than two
                        months: more than 25 well organized great meetings were held int
                        he different quarters of the city, mostly attended by several
                        thousands demonstrators and spectators, and hundreds of speeches were
                        delivered, all condemning autocracy as despotic &amp; tyrannical and
                        eulogizing liberty and constitutional government. About £2000 were spent on
                        the festivities and had not notables of Damascus with
                        the young Turks lately recommended their cessation they
                        might have continued for another month or more. It is to be remarked with
                        pleasure that all these gathering &amp; demonstrations were conducted most
                        orderly without any dispute or ill feeling among those who assembled.
                    Many corrupt officials were either dismissed or withdrew themselves.
                    The Alaybey of Gendarmerie, the Chief of Police, the Muhassebeji, six
                        Caimacams of Cazas, Moh.d P. Adm of Idara
                            Mejliss with about 30 other minor officials vacated their
                        posts, mostly to the general satisfaction of the public and it is debated
                        now among ‘Young Turkey’ adherents whether it would be
                        right to punish the officials who were led to bribery by the littleness of
                        their pay &amp; its frequent irregularity. Doubtless the proper course will
                        be followed in leaving this matter to the jurisdiction  of Parliament
                        when it assembles, and the ignorious[?] dismissal of the more corrupt,
                        rapacious &amp; outrageous among officials suffices for the moment.
                        Moreover, the vacancies are not being easily filled up by really good
                        substitutes, for such persons are at present rare, and often unwilling to
                        serve. 
                    Damascus Clubs &amp; associations, besides the Union &amp;
                            Progress number now five viz Hurriyet,
                            Ulema, Medical,
                            Commercial, Free Ottoman besides a
                            Shoemaker guild. the first two are showing much
                        activity wh.[ich] is likely to excite mutation . The misapprehension &amp;
                        with uncalled solicitude Ulema are anxious to
                            comcure &amp; uphold Islam against the liberal views of the
                            Young Turks, while the latter have no intention at
                        present to interfere with religious precepts. The first point of dispute was
                        about women’s wear which the Ulema wanted to be cut on a very simple mode,
                        one piece enveloping the whole body, and the liberals denied them the right
                        of interfering with this matter which should be regarded as pertaining to
                        individual free choice. In this campaign the Ulema were defeated but not
                        without their rivals using threats of applying force.
                    There is little record as to practical work effected [?] by other clubs
                        though their moral influence cannot be other than good.
                    
                    The Parliamentary elections are under preparation the last two months and in
                        some cazas the voters have already voted for the electors, but in
                            Damascus city this process will begin in a week’s
                        time. It is not even announced yet how many deputies will represent this
                        Vilayet in the Parliament but it is supposed that they will be seven or
                        eight. The Hauran people still reject their privilege
                        to elect a deputy and the efforts of the government in dissuading them from
                        this self-inflicted loss seem to be futile. The Mutessarif of
                            Kerak lately resigned on grounds of health, but
                        before doing so had been able to set going a local society or club for
                        instruction of the people of his district who indeed are little less
                        backward &amp;ignorant than this of Hauran.
                    The reforms in the various departments of the government proceed slowly. The
                            Municipality suppressed most improperly awarded
                        pensions paid to persons doing nothing for it and succeeded in amassing
                        about £3000 through various economies. The Public Instruction
                            Department formed a new chamber to consider the reorganization
                        of the educational system in this Vilayet. In the departments no special
                        reforms worth mentioning have been introduced but many are being talked of
                        &amp; discussed. 
                    The political exiles who had been releases or rehabilitated included many
                        persons of rank, both military and civil. Mushir Fuad
                            Pasha’s release was the occasion of great demonstrations in
                            Damascus, but the rehabilitation of others, with
                        a few exceptions, was not publicly noticed, for this disgraces persons were
                        always enjoying personal freedom  and a very few persons knew that they
                        were ‘Ikamet Mamours’ [iqāma maʾmūr]. The chief names among these were,
                            Nouri P. Ferik of Cavalry, another Ferik called
                            Nouri Pasha sent to live here without duties,
                            Ferik Ibrahim Pasha (those three Feriks kept for
                            Constantinople), Ferik Lt. Osman
                            P., Liva Behjet Pasha (those two died
                        recently), Colonel Bedri Bey (now of Liva
                            Bedri P. in Constantinople). The
                        Maàriz Mushiri [?] &amp; his assistant, and many minor officials or private
                        persons; such as members of the Bedr Khan family,
                        numbering more than a hundred. Further as reported in desp. No.
                            32, the Ismailians subjected to religious persecution were
                        pardoned. Happily no sort of disorder or riotous intention was displayed
                        here for the purpose of releasing prisoners and ordinary criminals
                        generally, as took place in some other places.”
                    Ḥijāz railway was completed in seven years and inaugurated on 1 Sep 1908.
                        four of the five battalions employed for earthworks on the line were allowed
                        to return to their garrisons. 
                    “about 1400 of these battalions on expiry of service were disbanded.
                        Moreover, the four battalions of the 40th Reg, sent to
                            Medina from this Army Corps in June
                            last, to guard the line, are also ordered back to their
                        headquarters. At present only two battalions are to be kept there to take
                        care of the line as regards repairs &amp; protection.” No aspirations to
                        commence construction beyond Medina due to increasing Bedouin raids
                        
                    “Public security in the Vilayet has been during the quarter satisfactory and
                        order was properly kept. The Bedouins have been quiet &amp; peaceful during
                        the summer, and only on two or three occasions made petty rais &amp; drove
                        or carried away animals or goods but the spoils were restored to their
                        owners without great difficulties.” Druze and Bedouins seem under the spell
                        of the government and calmly wait for the implementation of the promised
                        reforms
                    “the crops this year were in general very good and the grain harvest in most
                        of the districts of the Province was exceptionally abundant. The apricot
                        produce was above the average while walnuts were much below. All prices of
                        fruit and cereals are still high and the peasants this year will do well. An
                        exception might be mentioned as  as regards locusts which made a
                        perceptible damage in the Kalamoun
                            district but had a very slight effect in some other Cazas.
                        But the loss to the Vilayet in general has been small.
                    As respects trade, no special remarks need be made; strikes at
                            Beirut at the Customs and on local railways have
                        produced only exiguous loss here. With reference to the latter we may note
                        that public opinion judges that the smaller employés were underpaid, while
                        the profits of the Company &amp; of its directors were considerable and the
                        public at the same time ill served.
                    Public health has been satisfactory on the whole this summer, but the
                            Ain Fijeh water has not been received the general
                        approbation anticipated which is to be regretted, as theres is absolute
                        proof the it is the best &amp; purest spring water of al this neighbourhood.
                        Its distribution to all quarters of the city proceeds slowly.”
                
            
        </p>
         </body>
      </text>
    </TEI>
</teiCorpus>
