<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei/tei_oxygen.css"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
   schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../xslt-boilerplate/teibp_parameters.xsl"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader change="#" xml:id="teiHeader_1.d2e7">
      <fileDesc change="#" xml:id="fileDesc_1.d2e9">
         <titleStmt change="#" xml:id="titleStmt_1.d2e11">
            <title change="#" xml:id="title_1.d2e13">PRO FO 371/560, Turkey. Code 44 File 35258 - 39482, 1908</title>
            <respStmt change="#" xml:id="respStmt_1.d2e16">
               <resp change="#" xml:id="resp_1.d2e18">Transcription and encoding in TEI</resp>
               <persName xml:id="pers_TG">Till Grallert</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt change="#" xml:id="publicationStmt_1.d2e26">
            <p change="#" xml:id="p_1.d2e28">The digital text is freely available for re-use.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc change="#" xml:id="sourceDesc_1.d2e32">
            <p change="#" xml:id="p_2.d2e34">This text is a partical transcription of British consular reports from the
               consulate in Damascus to the Embassy in Constantinople as found in the National
               Archives, Kew Gardens, Great Britain (formerly known as Public Record Office)
               kept in the file PRO FO 371/560</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc change="#" xml:id="profileDesc_1.d2e39">
         <correspDesc change="#" xml:id="correspDesc_1.d2e41">
            <correspAction type="sent" change="#" xml:id="correspAction_1.d2e43">
               <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_2.d2e45">George Pollard Devey</persName>
               <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_1.d2e48">Damascus</placeName>
               <date when="1908-10-01" change="#" xml:id="date_1.d2e51">October 1, 1908</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="forwarded" change="#" xml:id="correspAction_2.d2e55">
               <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_3.d2e57">Sir Gerald A. Lowther</persName>
               <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_2.d2e60">Constantinople</placeName>
               <date when="1908-10-24" change="#" xml:id="date_2.d2e63">October 24, 1908</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received" change="#" xml:id="correspAction_3.d2e67">
               <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_4.d2e69">Sir Edward Grey</persName>
               <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_3.d2e72">London</placeName>
               <date when="1908-11-02" change="#" xml:id="date_3.d2e75">November 2, 1908</date>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile change="#" xml:id="facsimile_1.d2e82">
      <surface xml:id="facs_1">
         <graphic url="../images/pro-fo/371-560/DSCN7960_150dpi.jpg" mimeType="image/jpeg" change="#" xml:id="graphic_1.d2e86"/>
         <zone xml:id="facs_1_z1" ulx="3" uly="129" lrx="349" lry="222"/>        <zone ulx="91" uly="232" lrx="587" lry="296" change="#" xml:id="zone_2.d2e90"/>      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="facs_2">
         <graphic url="../images/pro-fo/371-560/DSCN7961_150dpi.jpg" mimeType="image/jpeg" change="#" xml:id="graphic_2.d2e95"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="facs_3">
         <graphic url="../images/pro-fo/371-560/DSCN7962_150dpi.jpg" mimeType="image/jpeg" change="#" xml:id="graphic_3.d2e100"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text change="#" xml:id="text_1.d2e104">
      <group change="#" xml:id="group_1.d2e106">
         <text change="#" xml:id="text_1.d2e108">
            <body change="#" xml:id="body_1.d2e110">
               <pb ed="print" n="1" facs="#facs_1" change="#" xml:id="pb_1.d2e112"/>
               <div n="2" change="#" xml:id="div_1.d2e114">
                  <head facs="#facs_1_z1" change="#" xml:id="head_1.d2e116">ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA<lb change="#" xml:id="lb_1.d2e118"/>CONFIDENTIAL</head>
                  <head change="#" xml:id="head_2.d2e121">[37930] No.1</head>
                  <dateline change="#" xml:id="dateline_1.d2e124">Sir G. Lowther to Sir Edward Grey.— (Received November 2.)</dateline>
                  <dateline change="#" xml:id="dateline_2.d2e127">No. 697.</dateline>
                  <dateline change="#" xml:id="dateline_3.d2e130">Constantinople, October 24, 1908</dateline>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_3.d2e134">Sir,<lb change="#" xml:id="lb_2.d2e136"/>I HAVE the honour to forward herewith a despatch from His Majesty's
                     Consul at Damascus reporting generally on events during the last quarter.</p>
                  <byline change="#" xml:id="byline_1.d2e139">I have, &amp;c.<lb change="#" xml:id="lb_3.d2e141"/>(Signed) GERARD LOWTHER</byline>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="print" change="#" xml:id="div_2.d2e145">
                  <head change="#" xml:id="head_3.d2e147">Inclosure in No. 1.</head>
                  <dateline change="#" xml:id="dateline_4.d2e150">Consul Devey to Sir G. Lowther</dateline>
                  <dateline change="#" xml:id="dateline_5.d2e153">(No. 51.)</dateline>
                  <dateline change="#" xml:id="dateline_6.d2e156">Damascus, October 1, 1908</dateline>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_4.d2e159">Sir,<lb change="#" xml:id="lb_4.d2e161"/>I HAVE the honour to submit herewith a general report on events during
                     the last quarter.</p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_5.d2e165">The great 'coup d'Etat' which took place in <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_4.d2e167">Turkey</placeName> on
                     the <date change="#" xml:id="date_4.d2e170">24th July</date> occupied all minds and arouses every emotion with
                     the proclamation of the Constitution, in <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_5.d2e173">Damascus</placeName> as in
                     all other important centres in the <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_6.d2e176">Empire</placeName>. </p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_6.d2e180">Among its results worthy of remark here were—<list change="#" xml:id="list_1.d2e182">
                        <item change="#" xml:id="item_1.d2e184">(a) Celebrations and festivities.</item>
                        <item change="#" xml:id="item_2.d2e187">(b) Dismissal or resignation of notoriously corrupt officials.</item>
                        <item change="#" xml:id="item_3.d2e190">(c) Formation of clubs and associations.</item>
                        <item change="#" xml:id="item_4.d2e193">(d) Parliamentary elections.</item>
                        <item change="#" xml:id="item_5.d2e196">(e) Reforms in various Governmental Departments.</item>
                        <item change="#" xml:id="item_6.d2e200">(f) Release or rehabilitation of political exiles or persons
                           disgraced.</item>
                     </list></p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_7.d2e204">Rejoicings and joyful manifestation are only coming now to an end, after
                     lasting more than two months. More than twenty-five well-organized great
                     meetings were held int he different quarters of the city, mostly attended by
                     several thousands demonstrators and spectators, and hundreds of speeches were
                     delivered, all condemning autocracy as despotic and tyrannical and eulogizing
                     liberty and constitutional government. About 2,000<hi rend="italic" change="#" xml:id="hi_1.d2e206">l</hi> were
                     spent on the festivities and had not the Notables of
                        <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_7.d2e209">Damascus</placeName>, with the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_1.d2e212">Young Turks</orgName>,
                     lately recommended their cessation they might have continued for another month
                     or more. It is to be remarked with pleasure that all these gathering and
                     demonstrations were conducted most orderly without any dispute or ill-feeling
                     among those who assembled.</p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_8.d2e216">Many corrupt officials were either dismissed or withdrew themselves. The
                     Alaibey of Gendarmerie, the Chief of Police, the Muhassebeji, the Secretary of
                     the Court of Sherá, six Kaimakams of Kazas, <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_5.d2e218">Mohammad Pasha
                        Adm</persName>, of <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_2.d2e221">Idara Mejliss</orgName> with about thirty other
                     minor officials vacated their posts mostly to the general satisfaction of the
                     public, and it is debated now among <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_3.d2e224">Young Turkey</orgName> adherents
                     whether it would be right to punish the officials who were led to bribery by
                     the littleness of their pay and its frequent irregularity. Doubtless the proper
                     course will be followed in leaving this matter to the jurisdiction   of
                     Parliament when it assembles, and the ignomious dismissal of the more corrupt,
                     rapacious and outrageous among officials suffices for the moment. Moreover, the
                     vacancies are not being easily filled up by really good substitutes, for such
                     persons are at present rare, and often unwilling to serve. </p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_9.d2e228">Damascus clubs and associations, besides the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_4.d2e230">Union and
                        Progress</orgName> number now five, viz., <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_5.d2e233">Hurriyet</orgName>,
                        <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_6.d2e236">Ulema</orgName>, <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_7.d2e239">Medical</orgName>,
                        <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_8.d2e242">Commercial</orgName>, <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_9.d2e246">Free Ottoman</orgName>, besides a
                        <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_10.d2e249">Shoemaker Guild</orgName>. The first two are showing much activity
                     which is likely to excite emulation . The Ulema, through misapprehension, and
                     with uncalled-for solicitude, are anxious to conserve and uphold Islam against
                     the liberal views of the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_11.d2e252">Young Turks</orgName>, while the latter have
                     no intention at present to interfere with religious precepts. The first<pb n="2" facs="#facs_2" change="#" xml:id="pb_2.d2e255"/> point of dispute was about women's wear, which the Ulema wanted to
                     be cut on a very simple mode, one piece enveloping the whole body; and the
                     Liberals denied them the right of interfering with this matter, which should be
                     regarded as pertaining to individual free choice. In this campaign the Ulema
                     were defeated but not without their rivals using threats of applying force.
                     There is no record as to practical work effected by other clubs, though their
                     moral influence cannot be other than good.</p>
                   
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_10.d2e258">The Parliamentary elections are under preparation the last two months, and in
                     some kazas the voters have already voted for the electors; but in
                        <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_8.d2e260">Damascus</placeName> city this process will begin in a week's
                     time. It is not even announced yet how many Deputies will represent this
                     vilayet in the Parliament but it is supposed that they will be seven or eight.
                     The <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_9.d2e263">Hauran</placeName> people still reject their privilege to elect
                     a Deputy and the efforts of the Government in dissuading them from this
                     self-inflicted loss seem to be futile. The Mutessarif of
                        <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_10.d2e266">Kerak</placeName> lately resigned on grounds of health; but
                     before doing so had been able to set going a local society or club for
                     instruction of the people of his district, who, indeed, are little less
                     backward and ignorant than those of <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_11.d2e269">Hauran</placeName>.</p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_11.d2e274">The reforms in the various Departments of the Government proceed slowly. The
                        <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_12.d2e276">municipality</orgName> suppressed the less properly awarded
                     pensions, and succeeded in amassing about 3,000<hi rend="italic" change="#" xml:id="hi_2.d2e279">l.</hi>
                     through various economies. The <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_13.d2e282">Public Instruction Department</orgName>
                     formed a new Chamber to consider the reorganization of the educational system
                     in this vilayet. In other Departments no special reforms worth mentioning have
                     been introduced but many are being talked of and discussed. </p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_12.d2e286">The political exiles who had been released or rehabilitated included many
                     persons of rank, both military and civil. <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_6.d2e288">Mushir Fuad
                        Pasha</persName>'s release was the occasion of great demonstrations in
                        <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_12.d2e291">Damascus</placeName>, but the rehabilitation of others, with a
                     few exceptions, was not publicly noticed, for this disgraced persons were
                     always enjoying personal freedom and a very few persons knew that they were
                           <q change="#" xml:id="q_1.d2e294"><foreign change="#" xml:id="foreign_1.d2e295">Ikamet Mamours</foreign></q>. The chief names among these
                     were, <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_7.d2e298"><sic change="#" xml:id="sic_1.d2e299">Mouri</sic> Pasha</persName> Ferik of Cavalry, another
                     Ferik called <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_8.d2e303">Nouri Pasha</persName> sent to live here without duties,
                        <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_9.d2e307">Ferik Ibrahim Pasha</persName> (these three Feriks left for
                        <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_13.d2e310">Constantinople</placeName>), <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_10.d2e313">Ferik Dr. Osman
                        Pasha</persName>, <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_11.d2e316">Liva Behjet Pasha</persName> (these last two
                     died recently), <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_12.d2e319">Colonel Bedri Bey</persName> (now of <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_13.d2e322">Liva
                        Bedri Pasha</persName> in <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_14.d2e326">Constantinople</placeName>). The
                        <foreign change="#" xml:id="foreign_2.d2e329">Maarif Mushiri</foreign> and his assistant, and many minor
                     officials or private persons (such as members of the
                        <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_14.d2e332">Bedrkhan</persName> family) numbering more than a hundred.
                     Further, as reported in <ref change="#" xml:id="ref_1.d2e335">despatch No. 32</ref>, the Ismailians subjected to
                     religious persecution were pardoned. Happily, no sort of disorder or riotous
                     intention was displayed here for the purpose of releasing prisoners and
                     ordinary criminals generally, as took place in some other places.</p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_13.d2e339">The Hedjaz Railway was completed before the end of August, as far as Medina,
                     1,300 kilom. distance from Damascus, together with Haifa branch of 160 kilom.,
                     making up a total of 1,460 kilom. laid in seven years, and inaugurated in the
                     1st September, the anniversary of the Sultan's Accession Day. After this
                     occasion the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_14.d2e341">2nd Battalion</orgName> of the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_15.d2e344">33rd
                        Regiment</orgName> and <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_16.d2e347">3rd</orgName> and <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_17.d2e350">4th
                        Battalions</orgName> of the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_18.d2e353">39th Regiment</orgName>, out of the
                     five battalions employed in earthworks, were allowed to go back to their
                     respective head-quarters, and about 1,400 of these battalions, on expiry of
                     service, were disbanded. Moreover, the four battalions of the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_19.d2e357">40th
                        Regiment</orgName>, sent to <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_15.d2e360">Medina</placeName> from this Army
                     Corps in <date change="#" xml:id="date_5.d2e363">June last</date> to guard the line are also ordered back to
                     their stations. At present only two battalions are to be kept there to take
                     care of the line as regards repairs and protection. it would appear that there
                     is no intention of immediately beginning to build the line beyond
                        <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_16.d2e366">Medina</placeName>, seing that the Bedouin tribes manifest
                     increasing activity against the projet : and it has been heard here that the
                     Bedouins to this side of <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_17.d2e369">Medina</placeName>, in case the other
                     tribes between <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_18.d2e372">Medina</placeName> and <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_19.d2e376">Mecca</placeName>
                     succeed in preventing such continuation, take of an intention to destroy the
                     line as far back as <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_20.d2e379">Medain Salih</placeName>, but certainly the
                     present Government will take measures to prevent such outrages. Probably the
                     coming year will be spent in constructing the bridges and other technical works
                     not yet made on the line. The thirty engineers with their chief,
                        <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_15.d2e382">Meissner Pasha</persName>, will await fresh orders as to what to
                     do in the future, and perhaps many of them will retire. </p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_14.d2e386">Public security in the vilayet has been during the quarter satisfactory, and
                     order was properly kept. The Bedouins have been quiet and peaceful during the
                     summer, and only on two or three occasions made petty rais and drove or carried
                     away animals or goods, but the spoils were restored to their owners without
                     great difficulties. It seems that the Druzes and Bedouins are to some extent
                     under the spell of the system of Government promising the application of strict
                     justice and <pb ed="print" n="3" facs="#facs_3" change="#" xml:id="pb_3.d2e388"/>the execution of law, and are calmly waiting to see the
                     results of this movement whilst there is no evident cause just now for arousing
                     dormant animosity.</p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_15.d2e391">The crops this year were in general very good, and the grain harvest in most of
                     the districts of the province was exceptionally abundant. The apricot produce
                     was above the average, while walnuts were much below. All prices of fruit and
                     cereals are still high and the peasants this year will do well. An exception
                     might be mentioned as regards locusts, which made a perceptible damage in
                     the <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_21.d2e393"><placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_21.d2e394">Kalamoun</placeName> district</placeName>, but had a
                     very slight effect in some other kazas. But the loss to the vilayet in general
                     has been small.</p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_16.d2e399">As regards trade, no special remarks need be made: strikes at
                        <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_23.d2e401">Beirout</placeName> at the Customs and on local railways have
                     produced only exiguous loss here. With reference to the latter we may note that
                     public opinion judges that the smaller employés were underpaid, while the
                     profits of the Company and of its Directors were considerable and the public at
                     the same time ill-served.</p>
                  <p change="#" xml:id="p_17.d2e406">Public health has been satisfactory on the whole this summer, but the
                        <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_24.d2e408">Ain Fijeh</placeName> water has not been received the general
                     approbation anticipated which is to be regretted, as theres is absolute proof
                     the it is the best and purest spring water of al this neighbourhood. Its
                     distribution to all quarters of the city proceeds slowly.</p>
                  <byline change="#" xml:id="byline_2.d2e412">I have, &amp;c.<lb change="#" xml:id="lb_5.d2e414"/>(Signed) <signatures change="#" xml:id="signatures_1.d2e416">G. P. Devey</signatures></byline>
               </div>
               <div type="type-written" change="#" xml:id="div_3.d2e420"><p change="#" xml:id="p_18.d2e421">(44/F37930/08)</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_19.d2e424">Therapia 697, 24 Oct 1908, Lowther to</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_20.d2e427">"Quarterly report on Damascus" Printed for consideration</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_21.d2e430">Inclosure: Damascus 51, 1 Oct 1908, Devey to Lowther. Printed version &amp;
                  type written version</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_22.d2e433">[…]</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_23.d2e436">"the great 'coup d'Etat' which took place in <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_25.d2e438">Turkey</placeName> on
                  the <date change="#" xml:id="date_6.d2e441">24th July</date> occupied all minds and arouses every emotion with
                  the proclamation of the Constitution, in <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_26.d2e444">Damascus</placeName> as in
                  all other important centres in the <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_27.d2e447">Empire</placeName>. Among its
                  results worthy of remark here were <list change="#" xml:id="list_2.d2e450">
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_7.d2e452">(a) celebrations and festivities</item>
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_8.d2e455">(b) dismissal or resignation of notoriously corrupt officials</item>
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_9.d2e458">(c) formation of clubs and associations</item>
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_10.d2e461">(d) parliamentary elections</item>
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_11.d2e464">(e) reforms in various governmental departments.</item>
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_12.d2e468">(f) release or rehabilitation of political exiles or persons</item>
                  </list> [xxx].</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_24.d2e474">Rejoicings and joyful manifestation are only coming now to an end, after
                  lasting more than two months: more than 25 well organized great meetings were
                  held int he different quarters of the city, mostly attended by several
                  thousands demonstrators and spectators, and hundreds of speeches were
                  delivered, all condemning autocracy as despotic &amp; tyrannical and eulogizing
                  liberty and constitutional government. About £2000 were spent on the
                  festivities and had not notables of <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_28.d2e476">Damascus</placeName> with the
                  <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_20.d2e479">young Turks</orgName> lately recommended their cessation they might
                  have continued for another month or more. It is to be remarked with pleasure
                  that all these gathering &amp; demonstrations were conducted most orderly
                  without any dispute or ill feeling among those who assembled.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_25.d2e483">Many corrupt officials were either dismissed or withdrew themselves.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_26.d2e486">The Alaybey of Gendarmerie, the Chief of Police, the Muhassebeji, six Caimacams
                  of Cazas, <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_16.d2e488">Moh.d P. Adm</persName> of <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_21.d2e491">Idara Mejliss</orgName>
                  with about 30 other minor officials vacated their posts, mostly to the general
                  satisfaction of the public and it is debated now among '<orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_22.d2e494">Young
                     Turkey</orgName>' adherents whether it would be right to punish the
                  officials who were led to bribery by the littleness of their pay &amp; its
                  frequent irregularity. Doubtless the proper course will be followed in leaving
                  this matter to the jurisdiction <pb change="#" xml:id="pb_4.d2e497"/> of Parliament when it assembles, and the
                  ignorious[?] dismissal of the more corrupt, rapacious &amp; outrageous among
                  officials suffices for the moment. Moreover, the vacancies are not being easily
                  filled up by really good substitutes, for such persons are at present rare, and
                  often unwilling to serve. </p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_27.d2e500">Damascus Clubs &amp; associations, besides the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_23.d2e502">Union &amp;
                  Progress</orgName> number now five viz <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_24.d2e505">Hurriyet</orgName>,
                  <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_25.d2e508">Ulema</orgName>, <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_26.d2e511">Medical</orgName>,
                  <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_27.d2e514">Commercial</orgName>, <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_28.d2e518">Free Ottoman</orgName> besides a
                  <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_29.d2e521">Shoemaker</orgName> guild. the first two are showing much activity
                  wh.[ich] is likely to excite mutation . The misapprehension &amp; with uncalled
                  solicitude <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_30.d2e524">Ulema</orgName> are anxious to <sic change="#" xml:id="sic_2.d2e527">comcure</sic> &amp;
                  uphold Islam against the liberal views of the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_31.d2e530">Young Turks</orgName>,
                  while the latter have no intention at present to interfere with religious
                  precepts. The first point of dispute was about women's wear which the Ulema
                  wanted to be cut on a very simple mode, one piece enveloping the whole body,
                  and the liberals denied them the right of interfering with this matter which
                  should be regarded as pertaining to individual free choice. In this campaign
                  the Ulema were defeated but not without their rivals using threats of applying
                  force.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_28.d2e534">There is little record as to practical work effected [?] by other clubs though
                  their moral influence cannot be other than good.</p>
               <pb change="#" xml:id="pb_5.d2e537"/>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_29.d2e540">The Parliamentary elections are under preparation the last two months and in
                  some cazas the voters have already voted for the electors, but in
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_29.d2e542">Damascus</placeName> city this process will begin in a week's
                  time. It is not even announced yet how many deputies will represent this
                  Vilayet in the Parliament but it is supposed that they will be seven or eight.
                  The <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_30.d2e545">Hauran</placeName> people still reject their privilege to elect
                  a deputy and the efforts of the government in dissuading them from this
                  self-inflicted loss seem to be futile. The Mutessarif of
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_31.d2e548">Kerak</placeName> lately resigned on grounds of health, but
                  before doing so had been able to set going a local society or club for
                  instruction of the people of his district who indeed are little less backward
                  &amp;ignorant than this of <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_32.d2e551">Hauran</placeName>.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_30.d2e555">The reforms in the various departments of the government proceed slowly. The
                  <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_32.d2e557">Municipality</orgName> suppressed most improperly awarded pensions
                  paid to persons doing nothing for it and succeeded in amassing about £3000
                  through various economies. The <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_33.d2e560">Public Instruction Department</orgName>
                  formed a new chamber to consider the reorganization of the educational system
                  in this Vilayet. In the departments no special reforms worth mentioning have
                  been introduced but many are being talked of &amp; discussed. </p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_31.d2e564">The political exiles who had been releases or rehabilitated included many
                  persons of rank, both military and civil. <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_17.d2e566">Mushir Fuad
                     Pasha</persName>'s release was the occasion of great demonstrations in
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_33.d2e569">Damascus</placeName>, but the rehabilitation of others, with a
                  few exceptions, was not publicly noticed, for this disgraces persons were
                  always enjoying personal freedom <pb change="#" xml:id="pb_6.d2e572"/> and a very few persons knew that they
                  were 'Ikamet Mamours' [iqāma maʾmūr]. The chief names among these were,
                  <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_18.d2e574">Nouri P.</persName> Ferik of Cavalry, another Ferik called
                  <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_19.d2e577">Nouri Pasha</persName> sent to live here without duties,
                  <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_20.d2e581">Ferik Ibrahim Pasha</persName> (those three Feriks kept for
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_34.d2e584">Constantinople</placeName>), <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_21.d2e587">Ferik Lt. Osman
                     P.</persName>, <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_22.d2e590">Liva Behjet Pasha</persName> (those two died
                  recently), <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_23.d2e593">Colonel Bedri Bey</persName> (now of <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_24.d2e596">Liva Bedri
                     P.</persName> in <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_35.d2e600">Constantinople</placeName>). The Maàriz Mushiri
                  [?] &amp; his assistant, and many minor officials or private persons; such as
                  members of the <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_25.d2e603">Bedr Khan</persName> family, numbering more than a
                  hundred. Further as reported in <ref change="#" xml:id="ref_2.d2e606">desp. No. 32</ref>, the Ismailians
                  subjected to religious persecution were pardoned. Happily no sort of disorder
                  or riotous intention was displayed here for the purpose of releasing prisoners
                  and ordinary criminals generally, as took place in some other places."</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_32.d2e610">Ḥijāz railway was completed in seven years and inaugurated on 1 Sep 1908. four
                  of the five battalions employed for earthworks on the line were allowed to
                  return to their garrisons. </p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_33.d2e613">"about 1400 of these battalions on expiry of service were disbanded. Moreover,
                  the four battalions of the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_34.d2e615">40th Reg</orgName>, sent to
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_36.d2e618">Medina</placeName> from this Army Corps in <date change="#" xml:id="date_7.d2e621">June
                     last</date>, to guard the line, are also ordered back to their headquarters. At
                  present only two battalions are to be kept there to take care of the line as
                  regards repairs &amp; protection." No aspirations to commence construction
                  beyond Medina due to increasing Bedouin raids <pb change="#" xml:id="pb_7.d2e624"/></p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_34.d2e626">"Public security in the Vilayet has been during the quarter satisfactory and
                  order was properly kept. The Bedouins have been quiet &amp; peaceful during the
                  summer, and only on two or three occasions made petty rais &amp; drove or
                  carried away animals or goods but the spoils were restored to their owners
                  without great difficulties." Druze and Bedouins seem under the spell of the
                  government and calmly wait for the implementation of the promised reforms</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_35.d2e630">"the crops this year were in general very good and the grain harvest in most of
                  the districts of the Province was exceptionally abundant. The apricot produce
                  was above the average while walnuts were much below. All prices of fruit and
                  cereals are still high and the peasants this year will do well. An exception
                  might be mentioned as <pb change="#" xml:id="pb_8.d2e632"/> as regards locusts which made a perceptible damage
                  in the <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_37.d2e634"><placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_37.d2e635">Kalamoun</placeName> district</placeName> but had
                  a very slight effect in some other Cazas. But the loss to the Vilayet in
                  general has been small.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_36.d2e640">As respects trade, no special remarks need be made; strikes at
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_39.d2e642">Beirut</placeName> at the Customs and on local railways have
                  produced only exiguous loss here. With reference to the latter we may note that
                  public opinion judges that the smaller employés were underpaid, while the
                  profits of the Company &amp; of its directors were considerable and the public
                  at the same time ill served.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_37.d2e646">Public health has been satisfactory on the whole this summer, but the
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_40.d2e648">Ain Fijeh</placeName> water has not been received the general
                  approbation anticipated which is to be regretted, as theres is absolute proof
                  the it is the best &amp; purest spring water of al this neighbourhood. Its
                  distribution to all quarters of the city proceeds slowly."</p>
                  </div>
               <div type="draft" change="#" xml:id="div_4.d2e653">
               <gap change="#" xml:id="gap_1.d2e655">[…]</gap>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_38.d2e658">"the great '<q change="#" xml:id="q_2.d2e660">coup d'Etat</q>' which took place in <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_41.d2e663">Turkey</placeName> on
                  the <date change="#" xml:id="date_8.d2e666">24th July</date> occupied all minds and arouses every emotion with
                  the proclamation of the Constitution, in <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_42.d2e669">Damascus</placeName> as in
                  all other important centres in the <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_43.d2e672">Empire</placeName>. Among its
                  results worthy of remark here were <list change="#" xml:id="list_3.d2e676">
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_13.d2e678">(a) celebrations and festivities</item>
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_14.d2e681">(b) dismissal or resignation of notoriously corrupt officials</item>
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_15.d2e684">(c) formation of clubs and associations</item>
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_16.d2e687">(d) parliamentary elections</item>
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_17.d2e690">(e) reforms in various governmental departments.</item>
                     <item change="#" xml:id="item_18.d2e694">(f) release or rehabilitation of political exiles or persons</item>
                  </list> [xxx].</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_39.d2e699">Rejoicings and joyful manifestation are only coming now to an end, after
                  lasting more than two months: more than 25 well organized great meetings were
                  held int he different quarters of the city, mostly attended by several
                  thousands demonstrators and spectators, and hundreds of speeches were
                  delivered, all condemning autocracy as despotic &amp; tyrannical and eulogizing
                  liberty and constitutional government. About £2000 were spent on the
                  festivities and had not notables of <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_44.d2e701">Damascus</placeName> with the
                  <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_35.d2e704">young Turks</orgName> lately recommended their cessation they might
                  have continued for another month or more. It is to be remarked with pleasure
                  that all these gathering &amp; demonstrations were conducted most orderly
                  without any dispute or ill feeling among those who assembled.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_40.d2e708">Many corrupt officials were either dismissed or withdrew themselves.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_41.d2e711">The Alaybey of Gendarmerie, the Chief of Police, the Muhassebeji, six Caimacams
                  of Cazas, <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_26.d2e713">Moh.d P. Adm</persName> of <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_36.d2e716">Idara Mejliss</orgName>
                  with about 30 other minor officials vacated their posts, mostly to the general
                  satisfaction of the public and it is debated now among '<orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_37.d2e719">Young
                     Turkey</orgName>' adherents whether it would be right to punish the
                  officials who were led to bribery by the littleness of their pay &amp; its
                  frequent irregularity. Doubtless the proper course will be followed in leaving
                  this matter to the jurisdiction <pb change="#" xml:id="pb_9.d2e722"/> of Parliament when it assembles, and the
                  ignorious[?] dismissal of the more corrupt, rapacious &amp; outrageous among
                  officials suffices for the moment. Moreover, the vacancies are not being easily
                  filled up by really good substitutes, for such persons are at present rare, and
                  often unwilling to serve. </p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_42.d2e726">Damascus Clubs &amp; associations, besides the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_38.d2e728">Union &amp;
                  Progress</orgName> number now five viz <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_39.d2e731">Hurriyet</orgName>,
                  <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_40.d2e734">Ulema</orgName>, <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_41.d2e737">Medical</orgName>,
                  <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_42.d2e740">Commercial</orgName>, <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_43.d2e744">Free Ottoman</orgName> besides a
                  <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_44.d2e747">Shoemaker</orgName> guild. the first two are showing much activity
                  wh.[ich] is likely to excite mutation . The misapprehension &amp; with uncalled
                  solicitude <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_45.d2e750">Ulema</orgName> are anxious to <sic change="#" xml:id="sic_3.d2e753">comcure</sic> &amp;
                  uphold Islam against the liberal views of the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_46.d2e756">Young Turks</orgName>,
                  while the latter have no intention at present to interfere with religious
                  precepts. The first point of dispute was about women's wear which the Ulema
                  wanted to be cut on a very simple mode, one piece enveloping the whole body,
                  and the liberals denied them the right of interfering with this matter which
                  should be regarded as pertaining to individual free choice. In this campaign
                  the Ulema were defeated but not without their rivals using threats of applying
                  force.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_43.d2e760">There is little record as to practical work effected [?] by other clubs though
                  their moral influence cannot be other than good.</p>
               <pb change="#" xml:id="pb_10.d2e763"/>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_44.d2e765">The Parliamentary elections are under preparation the last two months and in
                  some cazas the voters have already voted for the electors, but in
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_45.d2e767">Damascus</placeName> city this process will begin in a week's
                  time. It is not even announced yet how many deputies will represent this
                  Vilayet in the Parliament but it is supposed that they will be seven or eight.
                  The <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_46.d2e770">Hauran</placeName> people still reject their privilege to elect
                  a deputy and the efforts of the government in dissuading them from this
                  self-inflicted loss seem to be futile. The Mutessarif of
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_47.d2e773">Kerak</placeName> lately resigned on grounds of health, but
                  before doing so had been able to set going a local society or club for
                  instruction of the people of his district who indeed are little less backward
                  &amp;ignorant than this of <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_48.d2e776">Hauran</placeName>.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_45.d2e780">The reforms in the various departments of the government proceed slowly. The
                  <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_47.d2e782">Municipality</orgName> suppressed most improperly awarded pensions
                  paid to persons doing nothing for it and succeeded in amassing about £3000
                  through various economies. The <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_48.d2e785">Public Instruction Department</orgName>
                  formed a new chamber to consider the reorganization of the educational system
                  in this Vilayet. In the departments no special reforms worth mentioning have
                  been introduced but many are being talked of &amp; discussed. </p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_46.d2e789">The political exiles who had been releases or rehabilitated included many
                  persons of rank, both military and civil. <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_27.d2e791">Mushir Fuad
                     Pasha</persName>'s release was the occasion of great demonstrations in
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_49.d2e794">Damascus</placeName>, but the rehabilitation of others, with a
                  few exceptions, was not publicly noticed, for this disgraces persons were
                  always enjoying personal freedom <pb change="#" xml:id="pb_11.d2e797"/> and a very few persons knew that they
                  were 'Ikamet Mamours' [iqāma maʾmūr]. The chief names among these were,
                  <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_28.d2e799">Nouri P.</persName> Ferik of Cavalry, another Ferik called
                  <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_29.d2e802">Nouri Pasha</persName> sent to live here without duties,
                  <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_30.d2e806">Ferik Ibrahim Pasha</persName> (those three Feriks kept for
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_50.d2e809">Constantinople</placeName>), <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_31.d2e812">Ferik Lt. Osman
                     P.</persName>, <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_32.d2e815">Liva Behjet Pasha</persName> (those two died
                  recently), <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_33.d2e818">Colonel Bedri Bey</persName> (now of <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_34.d2e821">Liva Bedri
                     P.</persName> in <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_51.d2e825">Constantinople</placeName>). The Maàriz Mushiri
                  [?] &amp; his assistant, and many minor officials or private persons; such as
                  members of the <persName change="#" xml:id="persName_35.d2e828">Bedr Khan</persName> family, numbering more than a
                  hundred. Further as reported in <ref change="#" xml:id="ref_3.d2e831">desp. No. 32</ref>, the Ismailians
                  subjected to religious persecution were pardoned. Happily no sort of disorder
                  or riotous intention was displayed here for the purpose of releasing prisoners
                  and ordinary criminals generally, as took place in some other places."</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_47.d2e836">Ḥijāz railway was completed in seven years and inaugurated on 1 Sep 1908. four
                  of the five battalions employed for earthworks on the line were allowed to
                  return to their garrisons. </p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_48.d2e839">"about 1400 of these battalions on expiry of service were disbanded. Moreover,
                  the four battalions of the <orgName change="#" xml:id="orgName_49.d2e841">40th Reg</orgName>, sent to
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_52.d2e844">Medina</placeName> from this Army Corps in <date change="#" xml:id="date_9.d2e847">June
                     last</date>, to guard the line, are also ordered back to their headquarters. At
                  present only two battalions are to be kept there to take care of the line as
                  regards repairs &amp; protection." No aspirations to commence construction
                  beyond Medina due to increasing Bedouin raids <pb change="#" xml:id="pb_12.d2e850"/></p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_49.d2e852">"Public security in the Vilayet has been during the quarter satisfactory and
                  order was properly kept. The Bedouins have been quiet &amp; peaceful during the
                  summer, and only on two or three occasions made petty rais &amp; drove or
                  carried away animals or goods but the spoils were restored to their owners
                  without great difficulties." Druze and Bedouins seem under the spell of the
                  government and calmly wait for the implementation of the promised reforms</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_50.d2e855">"the crops this year were in general very good and the grain harvest in most of
                  the districts of the Province was exceptionally abundant. The apricot produce
                  was above the average while walnuts were much below. All prices of fruit and
                  cereals are still high and the peasants this year will do well. An exception
                  might be mentioned as <pb change="#" xml:id="pb_13.d2e857"/> as regards locusts which made a perceptible damage
                  in the <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_53.d2e859"><placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_53.d2e860">Kalamoun</placeName> district</placeName> but had
                  a very slight effect in some other Cazas. But the loss to the Vilayet in
                  general has been small.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_51.d2e865">As respects trade, no special remarks need be made; strikes at
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_55.d2e867">Beirut</placeName> at the Customs and on local railways have
                  produced only exiguous loss here. With reference to the latter we may note that
                  public opinion judges that the smaller employés were underpaid, while the
                  profits of the Company &amp; of its directors were considerable and the public
                  at the same time ill served.</p>
               <p change="#" xml:id="p_52.d2e871">Public health has been satisfactory on the whole this summer, but the
                  <placeName change="#" xml:id="placeName_56.d2e873">Ain Fijeh</placeName> water has not been received the general
                  approbation anticipated which is to be regretted, as theres is absolute proof
                  the it is the best &amp; purest spring water of al this neighbourhood. Its
                  distribution to all quarters of the city proceeds slowly."</p>
                  </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>